Guide to the James Lord Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1917-2003; Series II; 18.76 linear feet (48 boxes)
  - Writings of James Lord
    - "Picasso's portrait of Dora Maar in a striped dress," draft, autograph manuscript, 1998 (Box 60, Folder 575)
    - Plausible Portraits of James Lord
      - Draft, autograph manuscript, 2001 (Box 60, Folder 576)
      - Draft, autograph manuscript (copy), undated (Box 60, Folder 577)
      - "Discarded manuscript pages", undated (Box 60, Folder 578)
      - Foreword, autograph manuscript (copy), circa 2001 (Box 60, Folder 579)
      - Typescript (partial), corrected, undated (Box 60, Folder 580)
      - "Revised foreword," computer printout, corrected, 2002 (Box 60, Folder 581)
      - Proofs, 2002 (Box 61, Folder 582-587)
      - Proofs, 2002-2003 (Box 62, Folder 588-590)
      - Dead matter, 2003 (Box 62, Folder 591-592)
    - "Printemps," autograph manuscript, 1950s (Box 62, Folder 593)
    - "Remembering Dora Maar," autograph manuscript, 1998 (Box 62, Folder 594)
    - Rufus and Jack
      - Draft, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 62, Folder 595-596)
      - Draft, autograph manuscript (continued), undated (Box 63, Folder 597-598)
      - Computer printout, undated (Box 63, Folder 599-602)
    - Sacred Monsters, Sacred Masters, by John Richardson. Review by James Lord, draft, autograph manuscript, 2002 (Box 63, Folder 603)
    - "Saving Cezanne's Studio"
      - Drafts, autograph manuscript, 2001 (Box 64, Folder 604)
      - Related printed material, 2002 (Box 64, Folder 605)
    - Six Exceptional Women: Further Memoirs
      - "Letters from Mother: Used in A Maternal Ordeal", 1960-1986 (Box 64, Folder 606-610)
      - "Errieta's Risk," proof, corrected, undated (Box 65, Folder 611)
      - Proofs, some corrected, 1994 (Box 65, Folder 612-618)
      - Proofs, some corrected, 1994 (Box 66, Folder 619-626)
    - Some Remarkable Men: Further Memoirs
      - "46 Rue Hippolyte and after," draft, computer printout, 1995 (Box 67, Folder 627)
      - "Pages added to Remarkable Men but cut at Bruno's request," autograph manuscript (copy), undated (Box 67, Folder 628)
      - Setting typescript, 1996 (Box 67, Folder 629-632)
      - Proof, 1996 (Box 67, Folder 633-635)
      - Proof, 1996 (Box 68, Folder 636-638)
      - Contract, 1995 (Box 68, Folder 639)
    - Stories of Youth, proof, 2001 (Box 68, Folder 640)
    - "Vision of Alberto Giacometti," printed version, 1977 (Box 68, Folder 641)
    - [Untitled poem]. "For Dora," autograph manuscript, 1950s (Box 68, Folder 642)
    - [Various titles]. Reviews by James Lord, printed versions, 1960s-2000s (Box 68, Folder 643)
    - Unidentified writings, undated (Box 68, Folder 644-645)
  - Writings of Others
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Bernard, Bruce, "Thinking about Lucian Freud," printed version annotated by James Lord, 1996
    - Brunet, Sophie. Un portrait par Giacometti d'apres le livre de James Lord (Box 69, Folder 646)
    - Cole, Henry. Diary of A Young Poet (Box 69, Folder 647)
    - Eluard, Paul. Poem: "En Provence," typescript, signed, undated (Box 69, Folder 648)
    - Maurois, Andre. "Préface," autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 69, Folder 649)
    - Plante, David. "Harold Acton," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 69, Folder 650)
    - Sylvester, David. "The panels are still empty," galley proofs, 1964 (Box 69, Folder 651)
    - White, Edmund. "Trios," printout (copy), 1993 (Box 69, Folder 652)
- Visual Material, 1924-1964; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Organized into two subseries: Photographs and Drawings.
  Series III contains visual material that chiefly documents Lord's life and his mileau in France from the 1940s to the 1960s.
  - Photographs
    Arranged chronologically.
    - H.D. and Frieda Lawrence, and "Chapel at Taos where Lawrence's ashes are kept", 1924, undated (Box 70, Folder 653)
    - Giacometti photographed by Marie-Laure de Noailles, circa 1931 (Box 70, Folder 654)
    - Pablo Picasso, by an unidentified photographer, 1944 (Box 70, Folder 655)
    - Somerset Maugham, Bill Miller and Monroe Wheeler at Stoneblossom, 1945 or 1946 (Box 70, Folder 656)
    - Stephen Spender, 1948 (Box 70, Folder 657)
    - James Lord and Glenway Wescott, photographed by Monroe Wheeler, [1950s?] (Box 70, Folder 658)
    - James Lord and Jean Cocteau, Antibes, 1950 (Box 70, Folder 659)
    - Pablo Picasso, photographed by James Lord, 1950 (Box 70, Folder 660)
    - Mabel Dodge Luhan and her husband Tony, photographed by James Lord, 1952 May 14 (Box 70, Folder 660a)
    - Giacometti and James Lord, photographed by Henri Cartier-Bresson, 1960-1961 (Box 70, Folder 661)
    - Giacometti's portrait of James Lord (scrapbook), 1964 (Box 70, Folder 662)
  - Drawings and Prints, 1920-1958
    Arranged alphabetically by artist.
    - Arms, John Taylor. "St. Martin's Church, Preston, Hertfordshire," etching, 1941 October 9 (Box 70, Folder 663)
    - Cocteau, Jean
      - Drawing of Raymond Radiguet, pen, 1922 (Box 70, Folder 664)
      - Caricature of Pablo Picasso, pen, circa 1920 (Box 70, Folder 665)
    - Giacometti, Alberto
      - Etching for Edmond Bomsel bookplate, undated (Box 70, Folder 666)
      - Drawing of flowers in a vase, addressed "A James Lord ...", 1969 March 10 (Box 78, Folder 748)
    - Spender, Stephen. "Lago di Gorda," watercolor, 1958 December (Box 70, Folder 667)
- Audiovisual Recordings, 1982-2002; Series IV; 0.84 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to original audiovisual recordings is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Organized into two subseries: Sound Recordings, and Video Recordings.
  Series IV contains audiovisual recordings that relate chiefly to Lord's research on Alberto Giacometti.
  - Sound Recordings
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Reference copies of sound recordings are available.
    - Audio cassette 1: Drot interview, undated (Box 71, Folder 668)
    - Audio cassette 2: Bruno and Odette Giacometti, 1985 December 7 (Box 71, Folder 669)
    - Audio cassette 3: Giacometti interview on Prévert, undated (Box 71, Folder 670)
    - Audio cassette 4: France Culture, Interviews avec James Lord et Adrien Maeght, 1987 February 18 (Box 71, Folder 671)
    - Audio cassette 5: Lisa Palmer/ Annette Giacometti Symposium, 1988 November 29 (Box 71, Folder 672)
    - Audio cassette 6: Lecture by Michael Brenson at the Hirshhorn Museum in Washington, D.C., 1988 October 29 (Box 71, Folder 673)
    - Audio cassette 7: Radio France, Demarches James Lord, 1982 April 24 (Box 71, Folder 674)
    - Audio reels 1-4: Giacometti interview by Drot, undated; 4 reel-to-reel audio tapes (Box 71, Folder 675)
  - Video Recordings
    - "James Lord: Art and Passion", 2002; GENMSS790_0001; 1; 00:36:37 (Box 72, Item barcode 39002102370005)
    - "Balthus de l'autré côté du miroir", undated; GENMSS790_0002; 1; 00:54:48 (Box 72, Item barcode 39002102370021)
    - Unidentified (likely a film concerning Giacometti), undated; GENMSS790_0003; 1; 02:47:09 (Box 72, Item barcode 39002102370039)
      Most of this film is in French. There are some parts that are in English with French subtitles. The arte TV brand appears in the upper right-hand corner of the video.
- Personal Papers, circa 1950-2001; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series V contains fragmentary documentation of Lord's personal life and includes his passport, journal fragments and a sketchbook.
  - Sketchbook of drawings by James Lord, [1950s?]
    Includes a drawing inscribed "dessiné par Chagall."
  - Passport, 1960 (Box 73, Folder 679)
  - Fragment of journal, 1965 (Box 73, Folder 680)
  - Journal: "Loose pages, starting 2 September 1987, plus other random journal pages", circa 1987 (Box 73, Folder 681-684)
  - Fragment of journal, 1994 January 18 (Box 73, Folder 685)
  - Journal, 2001 (Box 73, Folder 686)
  - Giacometti scrapbook, undated (Box 82)
- Printed Material, 1949- circa 2003; Series VI; 1.67 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Organized by type of material.
  Series VI contains printed material relating to James Lord and his research. Clippings consists of writings by James Lord, reviews of works by James Lord, profiles of James Lord, and articles on Giacometti or other topics related to Lord's work.
  - Clippings: Writings by James Lord in The New York Times Book Review, 1967-1968 (Box 74, Folder 687)
  - Clippings: Reviews of works by James Lord, 1993-1999 (Box 74, Folder 688-692)
  - Clippings: Giacometti, 1960s-1980s (Box 74, Folder 693-694)
  - Clippings: Harold Acton, 1990s (Box 74, Folder 695)
  - Clippings, unsorted, 1980s-2000s (Box 75, Folder 696-711)
  - Magazines and journals containing articles related to James Lord, 1990s-2000s; Also stored in: Oversize, Box 78. (Box 76, Folder 712-725)
  - Barber, Samuel. Vanessa., 1957-1981 (Box 77, Folder 726)
    Bound with clippings and ephemera related to Barber.
  - L'Oeil, Volume 1, 1955, 1998, undated (Box 77, Folder 727)
    Bound with an autograph note by James Lord and a letter from Alberto Giacometti to Diego Giacometti.
  - Horizon, Volume 20, 1949, 1995 (Box 77, Folder 728)
    Bound with an autograph note by James Lord.
  - Metropolitan Opera Libretto: The Rake's Progress, 1953 (Box 77, Folder 729)
  - Books by James Lord (Box 83)
- Oversize Material, 0.33 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Poster: La Bête dans la Jungle, 1981 (Box 78, Folder 730)
  - Bernard, Bruce, "Thinking about Lucian Freud," printed version annotated by James Lord (Series II), 1996 (Box 78, Folder 731)
  - Giacometti and James Lord, photographed by Henri Cartier-Bresson (Series III), 1960-1961 (Box 78, Folder 732)
  - Clippings: Writings by James Lord in The New York Times Book Review (Series VI), 1967 (Box 78, Folder 733)
  - Magazines and journals containing articles related to James Lord (Series VI), 1974, 1995 (Box 78, Folder 734)
  - Clippings: unsorted (Series VI), 2000s (Box 78, Folder 735)
  - Giacometti, Alberto. Drawing of flowers in a vase (Series III), 1969 March 10
  - Sketchbook of drawings by James Lord (Series V), undated (Box 79, Folder 736)
- Restricted Fragile Material, 0.84 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Audiocassettes
    - Drot interview. Alberto Giacometti / Raymond Mason, undated; 1; 01:49:33; The program is distorted at times. Clicks, pops, and static can be heard. A high amount of hum is also on the tape. High background noise can be heard. The program ends abruptly. (Box 80, Item barcode 39002104889853)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Conversation with Bruno and Odette Giacometti, 1985 December 7; 1; 01:18:45; The program begins and ends abruptly. (Box 80, Item barcode 39002104889861)
    - France Culture, Alberto Giacometti. Interviews avec James Lord et Adrieu Maeght., 1987 February 18; 1; 01:01:31; The program begins abruptly. Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 80, Item barcode 39002104889887)
    - Lisa-Palmer/Annette. Giacometti symposium, 1988 October 29; 1; 01:02:29; The program begins and ends abruptly. High background noise can be heard on the tape. Static is present on the tape as well. Aduio drops out near the start of the program. (Box 80, Item barcode 39002104889895)
    - Lecture by Michael Brenson at Hirshhorn Museum, Washington, D.C., 1988 October 29; 1; 01:03:09; The program begins abruptly. High background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 80, Item barcode 39002104889903)
    - Demarches James Lord, 1982 November 21; 1; 00:16:20; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 80, Item barcode 39002104889911)
    - Giacometti interview on Prèvert, undated; 1; 01:28:50; The program is distorted at times. Clicks, pops and static can be heard on the tape. Audio was recorded at a lower level from 46:50 until the end of the tape. The program ends abruptly. (Box 80, Item barcode 39002104610671)
  - Audiotape Reels
    - Drot, Jean Marie. Interview with Alberto Giacometti, side 1, part 1, undated; 1 (Box 81, Item barcode 39002104889812)
    - Drot, Jean Marie. Interview with Alberto Giacometti, side 1, part 2, undated; 1 (Box 81, Item barcode 39002104889820)
    - Drot, Jean Marie. Interview with Alberto Giacometti, side 2, part 1, undated; 1 (Box 81, Item barcode 39002104889838)
    - Drot, Jean Marie. Interview with Alberto Giacometti, side 2, part 2, undated; 1 (Box 81, Item barcode 39002104889846)